<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Working Papers on </title>
    <link>https://gaston-lopez.github.io/papers/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Working Papers on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gaston-lopez.github.io/papers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How Do Governments Engage in Price Discrimination? Evidence from a Large-Scale Nationalization</title>
      <link>https://gaston-lopez.github.io/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gaston-lopez.github.io/1/</guid>
      <description>To understand the influence of interest groups and redistributive motives in state-owned enterprises, we study the nationalization of YPF, Argentina&amp;rsquo;s leading gasoline company. Descriptive analysis reveals a triple impact of nationalization. First, it led to lower prices, benefiting consumers on average. Second, it reverts economic price discrimination, by smoothing the correlation between markups and price elasticities. Third, it creates political price discrimination by charging lower prices in provinces that had political connections with the firm. Motivated by these findings, we develop and estimate a model of supply and demand of gasoline and recover the objective function of the State-Owned Enterprise (SOE), allowing for heterogeneity in how the SOE internalizes different groups of consumers and firms. Our estimates of the objective function reveal redistributive motives behind the nationalization. In comparison to a benevolent planner that internalizes the welfare of all consumers equally, the government chooses prices as if it only cares about low-income consumers in provinces that have political ties with the firm and middle-income consumers in all provinces. We then use the model to evaluate the firm&amp;rsquo;s response to policy alternatives, including privatization and rules that aim to limit SOEs&amp;rsquo; discretion in doing pricing, such as uniform pricing mandates. We find that rules are effective in limiting the influence of politics in SOEs&amp;rsquo; decision-making but are associated with high social costs: they mitigate half of the welfare gains generated by the nationalization and increase tax-payers costs by 10%. These findings shed light on the complexities of public provision, emphasizing the importance of politics and interest groups in shaping SOEs&amp;rsquo; actions and the role of SOEs as instruments for redistribution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reducing Consumer Inertia in Tobacco Markets</title>
      <link>https://gaston-lopez.github.io/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gaston-lopez.github.io/2/</guid>
      <description>Despite decades-long efforts to discourage smoking, the tobacco industry remains resilient partly due to consumers’ physical and psychological dependence. Recently, regulators have proposed nicotine caps and standardized packaging, known to decrease addiction and loyalty, the two primary sources of inertia in the market. In response, tobacco companies argue that lowering inertia will intensify price competi- tion, making cheaper alternatives available and raising consumption. We study the impact of reducing addiction and loyalty on cigarette consumption. To analyze this problem, we develop a dynamic model of price competition under inertia that considers firms’ product assortment. We adopt a computationally efficient equilibrium solution to make it empirically tractable and use rich variation from the Uruguayan tobacco market to estimate its primitives. We argue that equilibrium effects depend on how firms balance their incentives to capture new customers and profit from existing ones. If by reducing inertia, firms’ incentives to attract new consumers decrease enough; then prices might increase instead. Indeed, we show that sizable drops in brand loyalty lead to higher prices. Even if firms lower prices, the direct effect on consumers might dominate, as in the case of lowering addiction. Finally, we illustrate that eliminating inertia increases tax efficacy to deter consumption. In our context, taxes discourage firms from expand- ing their customer base, leading to higher tax pass-through. Hence, by lowering inertia firms pass less of the tax to customers. We contend this is positive for governments because they can reduce smoking prevalence while sacrificing less revenue.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Entry Under Demand Spillovers: Evidence from the Healthcare Industry</title>
      <link>https://gaston-lopez.github.io/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gaston-lopez.github.io/3/</guid>
      <description> </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
