<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Job Market Paper on </title>
    <link>https://gaston-lopez.github.io/job-market-paper/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Job Market Paper on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gaston-lopez.github.io/job-market-paper/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Do Governments Engage in Price Discrimination? Evidence from a Nationalization in Argentina</title>
      <link>https://gaston-lopez.github.io/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gaston-lopez.github.io/1/</guid>
      <description>State-owned enterprises (SOEs) have the potential to correct market failures, but they are also subject to the influence of politics and interest groups. We study this trade-off in the context of the nationalization of the leading gasoline company in Argentina. Descriptive analysis suggests that pricing patterns changed after the nationalization. First, the government charged lower markups on average, exerting less market power. Second, it engaged in less economic price discrimination, reducing the correlation between prices and consumers&amp;rsquo; willingness to pay. Third, it engaged in political price discrimination, charging lower prices in provinces that have political connexions with the firm. Motivated by these findings, we develop and estimate a model of supply and demand of gasoline under market power and recover the government&amp;rsquo;s objective function. We find that public provision leads to welfare gains but is also associated with redistributive motives. In comparison to a benevolent planner that internalizes the welfare of all consumers and firms equally, the government chooses prices as if it only cares about consumers in provinces with political ties with the firms and middle-income consumers in all provinces. Lastly, we use the model to assess the firm&amp;rsquo;s response to policy alternatives, including rules that limit discretion in decision-making and echo existing regulations in government agencies worldwide. We find that rules effectively reduce the influence of politics in pricing but are associated with higher costs: they mitigate half of the welfare gains generated by the nationalization and increase the tax-payers burden by 10%. These findings shed light on the complexities of public provision, emphasizing the importance of politics and interest groups in shaping governments&amp;rsquo; actions and the role of SOEs as instruments for redistribution.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
