<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Job Market Paper on </title>
    <link>https://gaston-lopez.github.io/job-market-paper/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Job Market Paper on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://gaston-lopez.github.io/job-market-paper/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How Do Governments Engage in Price Discrimination? Evidence from a Large-Scale Nationalization</title>
      <link>https://gaston-lopez.github.io/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gaston-lopez.github.io/1/</guid>
      <description>To understand the influence of interest groups and redistributive motives in state-owned enterprises, we study the nationalization of YPF, Argentina&amp;rsquo;s leading gasoline company. Descriptive analysis reveals a triple impact of nationalization. First, it led to lower prices, benefiting consumers on average. Second, it reverts economic price discrimination, by smoothing the correlation between markups and price elasticities. Third, it creates political price discrimination by charging lower prices in provinces that had political connections with the firm. Motivated by these findings, we develop and estimate a model of supply and demand of gasoline and recover the objective function of the State-Owned Enterprise (SOE), allowing for heterogeneity in how the SOE internalizes different groups of consumers and firms. Our estimates of the objective function reveal redistributive motives behind the nationalization. In comparison to a benevolent planner that internalizes the welfare of all consumers equally, the government chooses prices as if it only cares about low-income consumers in provinces that have political ties with the firm and middle-income consumers in all provinces. We then use the model to evaluate the firm&amp;rsquo;s response to policy alternatives, including privatization and rules that aim to limit SOEs&amp;rsquo; discretion in doing pricing, such as uniform pricing mandates. We find that rules are effective in limiting the influence of politics in SOEs&amp;rsquo; decision-making but are associated with high social costs: they mitigate half of the welfare gains generated by the nationalization and increase tax-payers costs by 10%. These findings shed light on the complexities of public provision, emphasizing the importance of politics and interest groups in shaping SOEs&amp;rsquo; actions and the role of SOEs as instruments for redistribution.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
